Guide to the Lloyd B. Saville papers, 1936-1979
Duke University. University Archives
Lloyd B. Saville papers 1936-1979
Duke University. University Archives
Saville, Lloyd B., 1913-1988
1.5 linear feet Extent: 1500 Items
Lloyd B. Saville was an educator, researcher, scholar and economist, specializing in economic history and theory. His career at Duke University spanned the years 1946-1979 and encompassed teaching, administration, research, and publication. Collection contains correspondence, manuscripts, grant applications, exam questions, printed matter, newspaper clippings, reports and other materials concerning international economic studies, seminars and societies, and Saville's teaching and research interests. Materials range in date from 1936-1979, bulk 1950-1979.
UA.29.02.0092
Language: Material in English French Italian
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
In off-site storage; 48 hours advance notice is required for use.
Provenance
The Lloyd B. Saville papers were received by the University Archives as a transfer in 1981-2006.
Biographical Note
Lloyd B. Saville was an educator, researcher, scholar and economist, specializing in economic history and theory, money and banking, statistics and insurance; however it was his studies of regional economic development, many of them done in Italy that led Saville to earn an international reputation in his field.
His career at Duke University spanned the years 1946-1979 and encompassed teaching, administration, research, and publication. He received several top research awards in the 1950s and 1960s, among them a Ford Foundation Fellowship for study in Rome; a Guggenheim Fellowship; a Fulbright Professorship; and a Duke Endowment Grant.
Saville's publications include several books on Italian economic development and numerous articles on regional economic development for professional journals.
Saville was also an accomplished amateur photographer whose interests also included music, nature study, and mountain climbing. He died in 1988.
Collection Overview
Collection contains correspondence, manuscripts, scholarly papers, grant applications, exam questions, printed matter, newspaper clippings, reports and other materials concerning international economic studies, seminars and societies, and Saville's teaching/ research interests. Correspondents include Calvin B. Hoover and economists in Italy. Materials range in date from 1936-1979, bulk 1950-1979.
Subject Headings
Saville, Lloyd, 1913-1988; Duke University. Dept. of Economics; Duke University -- Faculty; Economic development; Economics -- Study and teaching (Higher) -- North Carolina -- Durham
Related Material
Dept. of Economics records, 1947-1997.
University Archives, Duke University.
Craufurd D. W. Goodwin papers, 1963-1994
University Archives, Duke University.
Calvin B. Hoover papers, 1929-1988.
University Archives, Duke University.
Detailed Description of Collection
- Container List, 1936-1979, bulk 1950-1979., 3 Boxes
  - 2nd Duke American Assembly, May 1959 (Box 1)
  - Ball, Margaret, 1964 (Box 1)
  - Bibliography, General (Box 1)
  - Boston University, 1967-1968 (Box 1)
  - British Aging Project, 1959, undated (Box 1)
  - "C" (Box 1)
  - Cluster of Markets Concept, 1951, 1953, undated (Box 1)
  - Curriculum Vitae and Biographical Information, 1968, 1977, 1979, undated (Box 1)
  - Common Market Development and the Italian Crisis, 1965 (paper presented at 11th Conference on Teaching the Social Science, "The New Europe") (Box 1)
  - "A Comparison of some diverse systems of public finance" and "Diverse national developments in public finance" (Box 1)
  - Departmental Gift Campaign, 1978 (Box 1)
  - "Divergent Sectional Developments in Italy and the United States: An Exploratory Analysis," 1955-1956 (published in The Southern Economic Journal) (Box 1)
  - Duke Endowment Grant, 1965-1966 (for research in Tuscany: Center in Florence, Italy) (Box 1)
  - Ford Foundation (3 folders)
    - Departmental Grants, 1958-1960 (Box 1)
    - Fellowship Application, etc. (Box 1)
    - Faculty Fellowship, 1954-1955 (Box 1)
    - Fellowship Applications, etc. 1962-1963 (Box 1)
    - Faculty Research Fellowship, 1962-1963 (Box 1)
  - Fulbright Grant, 1959-1960 (Turin, Italy, Istituto Universitario di Studi Europe) (Box 1)
  - "G" (includes an interview with Crauford Goodwin, undated) (Box 1)
  - Guggenheim Application, 1958 (Box 1)
  - Guggenheim Fellowship, 1959-1960 (Box 1)
  - Hamilton, Earl J., 1954 (Box 2)
  - Hoover, C.B., 1950-1957 (Box 2)
  - Italian Letters, 1958 (Box 2)
  - Labor, carbons of questions (Box 2)
  - Lester, Richard. "An analysis of discrimination in university facilities," (seminar in honor of the retirement of Frank T. de Vyver), April 1974 (Box 2)
  - "N" (Box 2)
  - National Science Foundation, 1968 (Box 2)
  - Paris Seminar, June 23-24, 1960 (Box 2)
  - "R" (Box 2)
  - "Regional Economic Development in Italy," 1967-1969 (Box 2)
  - Research Council Application, 1974-1979 (Box 2)
  - Royal Economic Society, 1950 (Box 2)
  - "S" (Box 2)
  - Social Science Research Council, 1953 (Box 2)
  - Symposium on the History of Economic Thought, Duke university December 6-7, 1968 (Box 2)
  - Turin Seminar, 1959-1960 (Box 2)
  - Draft of dissertation
    - Saville, Lloyd. "Price Determination in the Gray-Iron-Foundry Industry," 1950 [dissertation - Saville's copy] (Box 2)
  - Contains scholarly papers, including an essay on the Cathedral at Pisa, personal copies of his M.A. thesis (Columbia, 1936) and Ph.D. dissertation (Columbia, 1950) along with preliminary paper for the dissertation and a précis and manuscript of an unpublished work, Price determination in the gray-iron foundry industry, (undated) based on his dissertation. (Box 3)
    - Saville, Lloyd. "Eighteen Years of a Company Union,"1936 [M.A thesis] (Box 3)
    - Saville, Lloyd. "Price Determination in the Gray-Iron-Foundry Industry," 1950 [Ph.D. dissertation] (6 folders) (Box 3)
    - Saville, Lloyd. "Price Determination in the Gray-Iron-Foundry Industry," undated (written as Assistant Professor of Economics at Duke University) (Box 3)
    - Saville, Lloyd. "Pricing Methods in the Foundry Industry," undated (Box 3)
    - Saville, Lloyd. "Pisa's Cathedral Complex: Benefit-Cost and Spin-Off of a Collective Good" (Box 3)
  - Printed Item: Ricardo, David. "The Principles of Political Economy and Taxation," reprint 1933 (Box 3)